Hello and welcome back.
We are almost done with our CRUD application.
However, if we go to our homepage we still see this default Laravel page.
We would like to change it and instead display the login page.
Let's see how we can do that.
We go to the terminal, we display the Route List
And we see, this is a login URI,
which is handled by the Auth Login Controller.
And within that showLoginForm.
OK.
So we go to the Routes File.
We comment this out as
we no longer need this.
WE can also comment this home controller.
And now we define a new Route for the homepage, which would be handled by AuthLogin Controller @
showLoginForm. Now if we reolad
this,
and now we can see the,
Login page as the homepage.
OK.
Another thing that we would like to change is, change this Laravel to our project name which is Storify.
Well how we can do that?
We go to the environment file.
And here we the APP_NAME
We can change it to Storify.
Save it. Before this is reflected,
We need to configure the cache. As we have learned before, we can do this using php artisan
config:cache
Now if we relaod it. It displays
Storify.
OK.
Now, instead of logging the first user, what we are going to do is we are going to login with the second
user for which we have some stories added previously.
So when I log in with this user.
Well we get to the stories page and we see that we are shown the stories for this user.
And if you go to the
view page,
This is working fine.
However, if I manually change the ID, let's say to 13.
Well, then I can view the story of our another user.
Mm hmm.
Well, this is not much of a problem.
However, if I go to the edit.
I can see the Edit Form and if I,
Let's see if I can change it.
I would change title to hacked, and I will change the body to Your Story
Has been
Hacked
by a malicious
user.
Let's see what happened when we click on Save.
Okay.
All right.
Let's save it now.
And it seems that story has been updated successfully.
Well, this isn't good.
We need to have some sort of check in our application.
What we are looking for is the Authorization process.
We need to check if a current logged in user is allowed to perform an action or not.
Well, this is different from authentication. As we've just seen,
The user might be authenticated, but he's still not allowed to perform a certain action.
So how we can implement this Authorization?
Well.
Laravel provides Gates and policies to determine whether a user is allowed to perform an action or not.
We will see how both of them work.
Let's begin with the gate.
You could define a gate in the App Provider and within that Auth Service Provider. Within this boot function,
you can define all the gates.
Let's define one. Gate
And I would include this at the top.
So you need to include this file at the top,
If your editor is not doing it automatically.
So we are going to define a Gate.
We are going to give it a name.
Let's call it,
edit-story.
And this is going to take a closure, which will have two parameters.
The first one is going to be the user and the second one is going to be the
Story that we need to edit.
Remember that the first parameter is always user, whether you pass it or not.
OK, so here we need to define, here we need to return true or false, depending upon whether a user
can update / edit a story or not.
So how we could do that? Well we need to make sure the User ID is equal to story user_id
So if the user_id column in the story is equal to the logged in User ID
that means user is allowed to perform that action and
In that case, we could return true.
OK.
Let's see how we can use it in the stories.
Controller.
Now, within this Edit method, I need to check whether a user is authorized to edit a story or not.
We could do that using Gate.
And don't forget to include this at the top, if your Editor is not already doing it.
And we could use authorize
And then the name of the ability,
That was a edit-story. If you remember over here,
this was the name of the ability.
And then we ask it, whether it is, whether the user can update this story or Not.
If you see here closely,
We have not passed it the User.
This will be automatically inserted by the Laravel.
So even though we have only passed it the story parameter, Laravel internally is going to handle it.
So we do not need to pass it.
So now if we go to our URL,
We see that we are getting a forbidden error.
And if we change our GATE again,
So let's say we
return a
True over here.
And.
Then we try to reload the page.
Now user can again edit the story.
So that means our Gate is working fine.
We again switch back to our original code and we see how we can define a Gate in the Auth service provider.
And then within the controller, how we can check if we,
We can check using the same Gate whether the user is allowed to perform an action or not.
Now, as you can see, we need to define multiple gates for all the actions.
And if he had more than one Eloquent models, we will need to define Gate for all of them.
This would clutter our Auth service provider.
A better way to define authorization, especially in the case of resource controllers, is to define
a Policy.
Let's comment our code.
And let's see how we can
Create a Policy.
If you go to our terminal,
We see a list of commands.
OK.
I made a mistake over there.
And within this make, we have a
Make policy command, which creates a new policy class.
Let's see
the help this one.
php artisan help make:policy
So we need to pass it the name of the class.
So let's do that.
And we are going to also pass the model using -m parameter and we know the name of the model is Story
php artisan
make:policy
And the name of the policy is going to be the story policy.
-m and Model Name story.
Well, it says the policy has been created successfully.
So let's see. we have a new folder policies inside app and within that we have a story policy.
OK.
Now within this story policy,
we have a number of methods and for each method
We need to return, true or false, depending upon whether a user can perform an action or not.
So let's do that.
First one is viewAny.
This one is for viewing the list of the stories.
So we are going to return true.
We do not need to check the user over here because within the controller we are always fetching the stories
for the authenticated user.
OK.
Now, this one is whether a user can view a story or not.
Now this is very similar to the Gate that we defined.
So we are going to say if a User ID is same as
story user_id,
then
User should be able to view a story.
For create we will just return. Any authenticated user can create a story. For update,
we will use the same code.
We will check if they user id is same as the
User ID of the story. And same thing we're going to do for the delete.
Well, we could ignore the restore or forceDelete
As they are not in the scope currently. Ok.
Now that we have defined all the methods, how we can check
Inside our controller.
Now the same way we checked how it, now the same way we did a check using Gate,
We need to do the same thing using policy.
We could do that using this authorize, name of the method.
So for
Edit it was
Update.
And then we need to pass it $story.
We do not need to pas it
they $user.
That will be handled automatically by the Laravel.
So now if we go to our Browser.
And reload it. We still get this 403.
So that means our policy is working fine.
OK.
Let's go to the listing.
Let's do the same thing to our Add story.
Let's say we decide that we no longer want User to be able to add story.
So within the story policy, we are going to
Return false
Instead of return true for the create. And within our controller we would again need to check,
Using this authorizes create, we do not pass any parameter.
So now we have disabled adding of a story. So now if a User go to Add Story,
He gets a 403 Forbidden.
Well, that's cool.
However, if we could find a way to disable this link itself, when our Policy is returning false,
That would be very cool.
Well, we could do that.
If you go to our view, we are going to make use of the $can directive. So we will say,
If a user can create,
and since we are checking for a story, we're going to say App\Story Class.
If User  can create a Story and then we are going to have endcan, Only then this link should be displayed.
Let's see if it is working or not.
Okay, it's not working.
Because,
Well, I need to change this
$ to @
Directives are always using @.
So let's try once again.
Sorry for the mistake.
So now we see,
that our Add link has been removed. And now if we change our policy and return true instead of return false,
We will see that it will be shown back again.
So how cool is that?
We could do the same for View, Edit and Delete as well.
We go to our index and we could use the same directive.
@can.
So for the view, it would be view.
And then we are going to pass it
the $story.
And endcan.
For Edit, again we could
pass it
The story and the
Name of the ability is going to be update.
endcan.
And for delete, it is going to be to Delete. $story
endcan
Just formatting it a bit. Now if we go to
Our
View.
Well, we are not going to see any difference.
We still see the all the three buttons. However,
Let's say that you have a new functionality and you want to disable the delete functionality. Instead
of removing the code from the controller and removing the code from the index.
You could simply make a change in your policy.
You could tell,
That we do not want to delete a story in any case.
So we can return a false.
And once we do that, this delete link would forever be gone.
So as we can see, it is so much easy by using the policy method.
Well, we have learned a lot in this lesson.
We have a much better control on our application.
And as you can see, we can easily change a lot of things by just changing the flag.
Hope you have enjoyed this lesson.
Thank you.